So the next thing we want to do in our game creation is make it competitive.
Because while it's fun to ski down a mountain, if we can't boast about our high score, then we have
a problem.
So in this lesson we are going to add a scoring system to our game.
Now you might be thinking, oh, I know how to do this.
I'll just create a variable called score and stick it at the top of the screen and I'm done.
Yes, that's good thinking and that would work.
But we've put lots of good work into this game and it's graphics, and we don't want it to be let down
with a basic looking variable that counts our score.
We need something exciting.
So we could start designing a cool score sprite that looks super nice and also creates some nice animations
and all.
But no, that's not what we will do.
Grab a pen.
Or type this somewhere.
I want you to write this down because it's very important and it will save you countless hours of time.
Are you ready?
Don't try.
Reinvent the wheel.
And he said again, don't try.
Now pin that somewhere you won't forget it.
Don't reinvent the wheel.
This basically means if something has already been done and someone has spent endless hours working
on it, don't reinvent it.
So what I'm saying is, while of course we could create this score sprite ourselves, what is even better
is if we could just use someone else's score sprite.
It's faster and it lets us apply our brain and our time to other parts of our programming.
In fact, this is what programming is all about reusing both your own code and open source code when
it is available.
Now, in the context of scratch, let's say you play someone's game and you think, hey, I really like
how they have that nice transition animation.
Or like the early example with the smooth movement engine.
Instead of trying to create your own smooth movement, you can use theirs in your own project.
Scratch allows you to do this, and the good thing with scratch is that it automatically gives other
people credit when you use their code in your project.
So let's do this for our own project.
Here you can see I found a nice soccer minigame.
And while the game is a little rough around the edges, it's still in beta after all.
You will notice that the score animation is really nice.
So how can we use this for our project?
Well, the first thing we need to do is click this see inside button.
And as you can see there is the score sprite we are looking for.
So just to make sure that you're on the same page as me, I want you to open up this project.
And you can do so by clicking on the link that is under the lesson.
Or you can just manually enter in this link.
If he still can't find it.
All you need to do is click file and load from your computer.
And under completed projects you will see this one called Soccer Mini Game.
So with the project open now, all we need to do is copy over the sprite.
And to do this, all you have to do is right click the sprite and then select export.
Here.
You can save it to whatever you like.
Just remember where you save it.
I will just choose downloads.
So now moving back to our ski game here, we can hover over this.
Choose a sprite and then click the upload sprite.
Now here you can see we have our score sprite which we can select.
So hitting open there you have it.
Our score sprite is now in our game and ready to use.
And think of all the time we've saved.
And with all that saved time, let's give the sprite a bit of customization so it better suits our game.
So moving into the costume editor, I'm going to delete all of these costumes and then click the upload
button.
Then moving over to the score folder you can see we have these nicer looking numbers.
So we can just select the first one.
Then hold down shift and click the last one.
And doing this will select all of them.
So now we can click open.
And there you have it.
Our new scoring design is imported.
So with that let's have a look at the code.
And as you can see this code is utilizing functions.
But let's quickly run through it so we have some idea of what's going on.
So when starters clicked, they are setting the score to zero.
Then they seem to have a loop, making sure the score doesn't go into the negatives.
Then over here they are running the setup function, which does a bunch of things like setting size
and costume and also creating a clone.
And then this clone calls another function and so on.
But for now we will leave it at that.
You're more than welcome to analyze this code for yourself, which I'm sure you can figure out with
all your already know.